This means we will realize that
the eye, ultimately, gives us
a massive illusion. For
example, you have
the impression that
I exist here in front
of you. You truly have this impression. In
fact, I am a mirage. Joanna Macy wrote a book. The
Earth, the planet, just
like oneself.
It's about
considering the Earth
perhaps as myself, with
a notion of
respect. And then
considering the Earth
as a beloved.
I will tell you about what
we call
the aggregates. And ultimately, we are a sum
of aggregates, a
momentary, impermanent, interdependent composition
that comes and goes.
Among these aggregates, we
talk about form, and we
talk about
earth, and also about the great game
of perceptions, because we're
going to work a bit
with this
great game of perceptions. Our
perceptions, if we observe closely, are just
like mirages.
Actually, there's something
very blurry. We think
because we have fixed things,
but ultimately it's
still quite blurry. So it's this
notion of interpretation,
how we see the things
around us. And so
the game that
has been built
is ultimately also
an interpretation. An interpretation of
things, of phenomena. Ultimately,
we are a phenomenology.
The idea is perhaps
that we could
slightly change this mode of perception.
Move perhaps to another mirage.
Perhaps a slightly bigger mirage. Perhaps as
big as the planet. If
we had this awareness
that we
are like this planet
and we become aware,
we would perhaps take a little more
care of this planet. Because
we are
in a society where
we are focused
on growth. But actually, we function completely in
this growth mode. We
are completely... caught up in it,
in this industrial growth, in this
growth that ultimately considers the world
as something infinite,
whereas we
are in a
finite world. There is
a real shift. And if I'm
telling you this, it's
because I'd like
to propose, to invite
you to
a slightly different
view. Either we manage to make this turn, or we
are heading towards a
collapse anyway. It's obvious from the fact
that it's about theories of emergence. And
it will be
emergence theories that are
always seen even within
the body itself. It
emerges and then
it collapses. And the society
we are in is
heading towards this tipping
point. I think that we,
as therapists, have a role to
play. A role to play.
to perhaps guide our patients, through this relief
of suffering that we do, but
also through this notion of opening
up a bit, you
see. Joanna Macy said, we will need three
things, three things
to perhaps make
this turn. The very
first thing is that
somehow, we must mobilize a
bit anyway. There have been movements
like this that happened, where
we have to say, no, it's
no. But
it's no, not especially,
you see, it's also no, enough. Second thing that
is important is creating new
ideas, new forms. This
brings us to
be creators, thinkers.
And this brings
us to a third
thing which is very important,
doing spiritual work. In any case,
this is what Joanna Macy proposes.
If these three conditions are
not met, we
won't be
able to make this
turn. We will be limited.
Ultimately, this is the work we do here.
That is to say,
developing a beautiful
awareness, a good heart.
It's asking ourselves a
bit the question how
we can slightly
reduce suffering too, not just yours. Because
most of
the time, we are
just
indulging in the pleasure of
our senses. And so this is
the notion I will propose to you, it is
learning to observe yourselves, learning to
observe your behaviors. We have this role to
perhaps learn to teach
others another form of pleasure.
than just our sensory
pleasures. Like discovering the pleasure of simplicity.
The pleasure of an authentic presence.
The pleasure that can come from the
relationship to things rather
than the possession of things. The
pleasure of contentment that comes
from a certain neutrality.
The joy of renunciation. At the
beginning, When you read Buddhist texts like
this, you see, the
Buddha, he said at the beginning, my heart was
angry at having to renounce.
And now that I have lived it, I
leap with joy in this letting go. My heart
leaps with joy at being
able to renounce certain things. I invite you
to reflect like this. What
could you abandon that
is actually adding suffering
to your life?
What adds suffering to
my life or even to others?
And so I think
that, as I say, as a therapist, we
perhaps have this role too, in a
way, of opening up
this awareness that we will have
to shift a bit towards this
level and maybe regain
a little simplicity. This
means that at some point, you will
almost feel joy in losing some of your
privileges.